This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the ITE
Computer Society by its software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Hello and welcome to another episode of
software engineering radio. Today we
will talk about the Amazon strands
agents SDK with Claire Legori. Claire is
a senior principal engineer at Amazon
Web Services where she works on
developer tooling and agentic AI. She
focuses on Kira and the Strand agents
SDK. She has spent 10 plus years
bringing amazing advancements to AWS and
to all our developers to our great
delight. Claire is also a contributor to
the Amazon builders library. Welcome
Clay to Software Engineering Radio.
>> Thanks.
>> Before we dive in, just a bit of a
primer on AI agents. You know, you know,
how would you define as an agent? You
know, what is an agent? I know it's been
going on for a while. So, where are we
today? And as developers, how should we
think about it?
>> I like to define it as three different
things. One, a model. Two, tools. And
three, a prompt. And I think pretty much
any agent system that you look at,
agentic framework, those are the three
core things that you need to get started
building an agent. And you know again we
all start off with chat GPD or cla the
web I guess you know entry what makes an
agent different from these typical chat
use cases.
>> There's all kinds of use cases you can
do with a with agents beyond chat. I
actually think we you know for a while
there we got very stuck on chat being
the only agent use case. But you know I
see a lot of customers automating
things. Many many teams at Amazon are
automating operations, doing ticket
troubleshooting, things like that. We're
seeing customers automating business
processes as well as of course chat.
Very common today. Obviously, coding
agents are very common today. But
generally I think compared to uh
something like an outofthe-box agent
like chat GPT building your own agent
gives you a lot more control over what
is the prompt, what are the models and
what are the tools. You can build tools
yourself. You can pull tools off the
shelf with uh MCP servers. But generally
you have a lot more control over what it
is you want that agent to do and what
success looks like.
>> Fair enough. Now, I guess that's a
really good segue into what we're doing
here. Strands SDK, I'd love to hear the
origin story. How did it come about?
When, where, or how?
>> I was working on a product called Amazon
Q developer in let's see two two years
ago now. And that was the time around
I'm trying to think back maybe Claude
sonnet 2 [laughter]
maybe maybe three but but at that time
you know the models were not very
reliable. They were great for chatting
back and forth, but when you wanted to
actually automate something like tool
selection, tool execution, coding, they
weren't very reliable. I mean, we
started back on Claude 2 where they
hadn't actually yet enabled you to put
tools into a tool section that was
structured. And so you just had to
describe your tools in markdown in your
system prompt. And then you would try to
get the model to give you the response
that tool it wanted to select in a very
specific format. So you could parse it
out of this natural language string. But
of course it wouldn't do it. So you
would try to give it parse the JSON that
it was giving you, but it would put, you
know, a sentence at the beginning like
here's my tool selection. That would
screw up your parsing and you would have
to give it feedback. And so we started
building simple loops to improve
reliability of these agents which looked
a lot like trying to parse the the
response and then telling the the model
what the parsing error was so it can fix
itself. And we saw these wild
productivity gains just with those
simple techniques of just giving the the
model feedback for reliability. But then
we started to models started to get
pretty good. They started to train on
model selection. They started to train
on actually modeling tools and tool
selection into a separate part of the of
the inference request. We didn't need
all of that scaffolding anymore. And we
also started to see that models started
to get pretty good at tool selection.
This was somewhere around I would say
sonnet 3.5 was where we saw it start to
get really good at at model selection.
And by that point we had built up all of
this scaffolding. We had built up prompt
pipelines where we tried to put the
perfect rag content into the prompt
ahead of giving it to the model. We had
done all of this work around, you know,
parsing the model's response and we
found that as the models were getting
better and better, we were actually
making reliability and power of what the
agent could do worse because we were
kind of artificially constraining the
model. So that was really the the key
aha moment behind what turned into
strands was what if we just throw away
all of the scaffolding and go towards
what we called a model driven approach
where you give a simple prompt. You give
the tools and you and you have the model
and you let the model choose the tools
choose the context that it needs. So as
an example, we stopped doing these these
mega prompt pipelines where we would try
to query from rag the perfect content
that context that the model would need
and instead provided rag as a tool and
so it would come up with the query for
rag pretty well. It it knew what it
needed to get. One really specific
example was we had an agent at the time
that was for uh querying the AWS
documentation, answering questions about
AWS and the rag database was about was
just the AWS documentation. But we found
out that the agent already knew so much
about AWS that the rag content, the kind
of proactive rag context was actually
confusing the model. there would be an
entry that wasn't really all that
related and it would just kind of zero
in on that and and it was almost like it
was kind of doubting its own its own
context that it had in its training
data. And we found that once we got rid
of that, sometimes it would query the
rag database and sometimes it would just
use its own training data. And so we
found that the the quality and the
accuracy actually went way up once we
stopped trying to proactively give all
this.
>> I would love to hear about the origin
story of Strand's um SDK. How did it
come about? What was it trying to solve?
What were the pain points? Well, I
started building agents as part of a
product called Amazon Q developer three
years ago now, I think. And that was the
time of Claude 2 before models had
really been trained on this idea of
tools. You could provide a set of tools
and you could have the model select a
set of tools. So, we had all of this
scaffolding around trying to get models
to understand tools and to tell us what
tools it wanted to run. We had all of
the scaffolding around
describing the tools in JSON inside of
the prompt and then we would try to get
it to respond with JSON about what tool
it wanted us to choose and we would have
to try to parse that. But the models at
the time were very obsessed with natural
language and so they would always say
here is your JSON or here is the tool
I'd like you to run and that would break
all of our parsing. But we found that we
started just adding these kind of retry
loops around that. We started parsing
the JSON and then giving that JSON parse
error back to the model and we found
that the models were actually really
adapted to fixing themselves on the next
time they would be able to provide the
correct JSON. So I think that was one
learning was the models dealt with
feedback really well. The second was
around the time that Sonnet 3.5 came
out. This was when models now had
structured ways for you to produce to
give them the tools and structured ways
to tell you what tools it wanted you to
run. And by that time, we had built up
so much scaffolding. We had these
massive prompt pipelines that tried to
pull from a rag database the exact right
context. And we had all of this logic
about what context went into the prompt
and where. And we found that with later
models, we were actually making the
accuracy and the power of these agents
worse. We weren't taking full advantage
of the evolution and the power of the
latest models. And so the big aha moment
was let's throw all of this away. Let's
see what the model can do itself. Let's
just give it a simple prompt. Let's give
it tools including access to the rag
database as a tool. It can figure out
what information it wants to go get. One
example was we had all of the AWS
documentation in a rag database and it
could choose to go get in new
information or it could choose to rely
on its training data for the model. And
we found that all of a sudden we were we
had these much more powerful agents and
they were simpler and they were quicker
to build because we didn't have to build
all of the scaffolding. We could just
provide prompt tools and choose the
model. And that was the kernel that led
to strands agents. That's that we
started building our own agent framework
to do that to take on this model driven
approach and simplicity approach to
building agents. Probably about a year
later, we looked at the success that
we'd had internally. We were shipping
agents in a matter of weeks. The QCLI,
which is now the Curo CLI, we shipped it
in three weeks um using this internal
framework. And so we decided let's
release this in open source so that many
more people can take advantage of this
this approach that enables you to take
full power advantage of the full power
of the model advantage of the full
capabilities of the model. That was last
May I think that we went that we open
sourced it and and since then we've had
over 25 million downloads. So it's been
great to see the community pop up around
it.
>> Nice. You know, I feel like I have a lot
of amnesia because now that you
mentioned it, I I can recall the pain of
having to describe what JSON looked like
in plain English, right? So, so, so the
model would spit out, you know, a
closing brace for, you know, matching
the open brace and and it would get
subtle things wrong like adding back
ticks all over the place. And now we're
at a place where you just give it a
contextfree grammar and and lens can
generate amazingly, you know,
syntactically correct outputs. What a
crazy 18 months. [laughter]
You know, it's interesting that you
mentioned model driven approach. Um, as
opposed to what? As opposed to like
stepdriven, manual, like, you know, if
you were to kind of call this something
different, what is it like, you know?
>> Yeah. I see two approaches that people
take to building agents that seem way
more complex than they need to be. One
is building a ton of custom
orchestration around the model. And
that's what I described around all of
the scaffolding that we had built around
models that over time the models made
all of it unnecessary. With the model
driven approach,
you don't really need to change anything
about your agent to start taking
advantage of a new model and all of its
capabilities. you just have to change
the model id equals uh line to start
taking advantage because you don't have
all of this orchest custom orchestration
that's now been made unnecessary. The
other thing that I see people building
is workflows. A lot of folks are
building things that they want to add
determinism to. Uh they want to take
advantage of these models but they also
want to do determinism, right? And
there's a lot of use cases where you do
need a lot of determinism, but it would
be great to automate with agents. So
things like booking an airline, wanting
to automate flight crew assignments to
flights, very hard to do, needs a lot of
determinism. There's a lot of rules
around it, right? There's unions and all
kinds of things. financial services
companies I see trying to automate
things like mortgage processing, loan
approvals, transactions,
and all of these things have are pretty
risky in terms of, you know, if you
don't do the right thing, if you don't
verify someone's income prior to
approving a loan, big risk for the
company, right? And so, a lot of folks
kind of fall back on what we know as
software engineers. We know workflows.
We know procedural code effectively. So
we want to build for loops. We want to
build if statements. We want to build a
while loops. And I actually find that
with agents, it's important to think a
little bit differently. This comes back
to some of the additional features that
we've been building into Strands since
our launch last May. It's hard to
believe that it's almost a year now, but
I would say Strand is transitioning much
more into an agent harness, meaning
we've been adding the life cycle hooks,
the context management that you need in
order to build a more reliable agent.
Maybe recently we released a feature
called steering. And this is my personal
answer, I guess, to workflows. I think
that workflows maybe appear to give you
determinism, but in practice they're
actually really difficult and there are
a lot of scaffolding. Again, I've seen a
lot of workflows developed inside of
Amazon that over time again they just
make it less able to take advantage of
model improve model capabilities and
almost make it worse in some cases. So
we steering takes a different approach
where let's take the example of loan
processing for example you want to
verify income before actually approving
a loan. The model might often do those
things in the right order but sometimes
is not going to do those things in the
right order. So as engineers we fall
back on our procedural knowledge right
we say okay let's create an if statement
in there and let's ensure that the
income verification came back with this
value if so continue to loan approval
but that ends up being very brittle is
what we find. So you might have asked
the agent to do loan verific uh loan
approval or you might have asked it just
a question about what's the risk of this
loan and so you end up with these very
brittle single use case agents with
steering instead you get to define rules
about certain restrictions on the agent
things like it must call a loan if it's
going to approve a loan it must first
check the value the user's income and it
must be above this limit or else it
cannot call this this loan approval tool
and that it kind of flips how we think
about software execution on its head
where it's just in time verification of
what has already happened as opposed to
when I'm building the agent I'm going to
say exactly the set of steps that it
needs to take like a workflow We found
that it can actually produce better
results, better accuracy than workflows
can, which is super exciting, but it's
it's a very different mindset than what
we're used to with workflows.
>> Interesting. Well, you know, it's funny
you mentioned the steering hooks because
looking at the efficacy of it has been
is being is pretty pretty impressive.
Right now if you take the traditional
agent harness but you know something
that's not rulebased but still a harness
that calls tools you know invokes the
model as life cycle looks where like
just to kind of the baseline where does
the agent harness end where did you find
strands was kind of leveling out
leveling out at where you got with the
your latest invocation uh latest
incarnation of the agent harness
>> one of the biggest changes the
differences that we see and I And I'll
focus on the steering because I think
overall, you know, we're really working
backwards from customers who are trying
to automate business processes. We see
that as one of the biggest use case
right now for agents. We have the coding
agents like the coding agents are out
there. Those are the biggest harnesses
we know of, right? That we see every day
on social media and in our lives, right,
as as software engineers. Those are what
we're using. But we find that most
valuable agents out there are probably
automating business process. Often get
asked, what is the difference between
hooks, which pretty much every agent
harness has, and steering? Very naively,
they look the same, right? I'm going to
inject myself into the agent right
before a tool calls and and do
something. One of the biggest changes is
hooks will only give you context about
what is the thing it's about to go do
and you can say this is dangerous or
this is not dangerous or I want to allow
this or I don't want to allow this. We
see this often with coding assistants,
right? You get a hook and you can say, I
don't want to allow RM RF star [snorts]
and I can block that with a hook, right?
Steering gives you the full trajectory
of everything the agent has already
done. And as it turns out, for
automating a process, that's super
important because you're able to express
things like if you're about to go
approve that loan, call the loan
approval tool. Then in that steering
hook, I need to see if it's already
verified income, if it's already called
that tool and what the value is that it
came back with. Um, some of the other
things that we see is models are
sometimes apt to hallucinate inputs.
There's a lot of use cases, right,
around taking an output from one tool
and providing it as an input to another
tool. Let's say you know a user ID maybe
you request you retrieve the user ID
from one tool you provide it in another
bad things happen when you hallucinate a
user ID in the other tool right as input
and so with steering you can you can see
in that hook when it's about to call
that tool and provide that user ID does
this user ID actually match what was
outputed another tool so it's super
important for reducing hallucinations as
well not every agent use case needs that
level of control but I find that there
are so many use cases around automating
business process ensuring there's you
know low hallucination rate handling
data appropriately that steering helps
so much more than workflows
>> about hooks you mentioned that today
hooks will tell you or at least will
signal what is happening next what is
the challenge in getting that context I
guess context in a loose loose way about
how it got there and where and you know
why it got there and passing that as
well for the hook implementer to act on
and why isn't that possible today
>> the key that we've added is what we call
the ledger so a recording of everything
that the agent has done and in a general
agent harness you can probably build
that up yourself with hooks like you can
inject yourself into every single thing
that the that the agent is doing and and
build that up yourself but strand plans
provides it out of the box and also
provides out of the box a few steering
providers that you can also use out of
the box. Things like an LLM as a judge
is a super valuable tool and strands
makes it really easy to just provide a
prompt as a steering provider and
evaluate what is what has the agent done
and what is it about to do and is that
okay? And how would this relate or how
common is it to various kinds of memory
that an agent might maintain or a
developer might provide as a sidecar?
>> So are you asking how is it different
from memory?
>> You were to maintain your own ledger
which which you probably wouldn't but I
mean if you were to maintain your own
ledger or keeping track of that history
of what has happened so far and what got
you here, what would you say would be
the parallels or similarities and
differences between let's say a memory
system? I do see a lot of interesting
work around turning agent trajectories
into memory. I think of memory as
somewhat maybe a naive way to think
about it is a a summarization or pulling
out nuggets of things in natural
language that can be retrieved later and
analyzing an agent tra trajectory is one
way to do that. Right? Looking at all of
the tool calls that it's done. We've
actually seen uh interesting experiments
internally around saving agent
trajectories as memory. So this gets
really interesting where often when an
agent figures out a way to do something,
you kind of want to remember that so it
doesn't have to figure it out again. So
there's I have an example where we had a
use case for this was again a set of
APIs or AWS APIs more of an AWS use case
where particular API within AWS requires
you to go and gather a bunch of
information from other APIs in order to
call it. You have to call like I'm not
kidding 18 APIs in order to gather all
of the information that it needs. And so
that's very challenging to get and
especially at the time was very cha with
earlier models was very challenging to
to reliably get an agent to call 18
tools all of the right tools before
calling that API gathering all of the
right information. And so we started to
save trajectories that in a semantic in
a vector database keyed by what was the
prompt that led to that trajectory. And
as it turns out, models are very good at
transferring knowledge. So even if a
prompt wasn't exactly the same as what
was in this semantic search, it could
retrieve something similar and then kind
of adapt the agent trajectory to make
the the right tool calls for the
particular use case it was working on.
So I think that's super interesting
where you can also add a little bit of
determinism for common use cases. Let's
say your agent has the same use case 80%
of the time coming in. saving that
trajectory as a type of memory but more
procedural memory than what we typically
think of memory as like these natural
language nuggets getting better
determinism and and even better
efficiency right because it has kind of
the answer the procedure it needs to
take right away.
>> Interesting. So it sounds like if you
know the prompt then you can look at the
most similar close enough prompts you
know kind of raggish or you know or or
vector search
>> and you would use that to see what are
the similar things. Is there a scenario
where these similar looking prompts they
might key to the same kind of trajectory
but over time the similarity would just
drift. Would that ever happen? Did that
>> and you can even think about you know
maybe later models find a more optimal
way to solve that problem too. Right? So
you kind of have to think about are you
going to expire some of those entries
over time? Are you going to re-evaluate
some of those entries over time or you
know not provide that rag effectively
rag tool to the agent and see if it
comes up with something more more
optimal more efficient over time because
again you don't want to get into this
place where you've built all the
scaffolding you have all of this data
that's effectively generated by an older
model and it's just making your system
worse. The challenge in the agent
building space is that the models have
these massive leaps. what seems like
every three to six months now. And so,
you know, potentially what you built or
what you generated three to six months
ago is now potentially making your agent
worse than it could be with the latest
models.
>> In an industry where demand for verified
skill has never been higher, prove you
have the foundation to [music] deliver
results with the ITE Computer Society's
new software professional certification
for emerging professionals.
Give your career the head start it
deserves. Visit
computer.org/certification
today.
You know, I think we've talked about
tools so many times in this episode
already, but before I jump to it,
there's one thing I I want to ask about
one of the hooks, one of the problems
that steering hooks were good at solving
the problem of handoff. You mentioned,
you know, hallucinations. You know, you
don't want to have the wrong user ID
being passed across tools, right? How
does strands kind of keep me even with
having the trajectory and the memory and
the history? What goes on with strands
and steering hooks to actually ensure
that verification is accurate.
>> One of the things that I appreciate
about steering hooks is that it is
entirely or it can be entirely
deterministic. I talked about LLM as
judge earlier, but it can just be Python
code. And so you can deterministically
create this steering hook. Unit does the
be Jesus out of it, right? To make sure
that the validation is correct. You can
use things like, you know, something
like Rego or Cedar to actually do
something that's verifiably correct if
you want. So you can get a lot of value
out of kind of injecting this
deterministic check in the middle. I
recently published some findings from a
project that I did where I wrote most of
the steering hooks using just plain
Python and I was able to get 100%
accuracy across 600 evaluation runs and
I was showing I think workflows only
achieved about 80% accuracy and then a
simple prompt was nowhere near that of
course but I found that that 100%
accuracy effectively comes from that
determinism that you are injecting in
there. Being able to deterministically
look at what were the inputs and the
outputs of the tools, which tool outputs
are s significant to you, right? Which
ones are critical and that's only
something that the agent developer
really knows by looking at the tools and
what's the data being passed between. So
that's [snorts] where it really becomes
specific to the agent. Like I can't give
you a
general checker of how the tool outputs
link to the tool inputs but you can
provide you know your own knowledge of
the data that is transferring between
these tools and that the agent is
handling about which ones need to be the
same absolutely and which ones are kind
of you know natural language that like
my example agent that I was evaluating
with steering hooks did have some
natural language things like it would
send an email to the user and I'm happy
for the agent to come up with natural
language to send to the to the user and
in that case I used an LLM as judge just
to make sure that the tone was was
correct it wasn't rude or anything and
then what I was able to do very
deterministic checks for the actual data
handling in between the tools
>> in this evaluation run I guess
evaluation set how did you choose the
members of that evaluation set
>> so I took a a sample project and I or I
built a sample project where it had
different rules that it needed to
follow. I'm trying to remember. I think
there were four types of rules and I I
think these generally map to a lot of
what I see people trying to do in
automating with agents, automating
business process. One is tool ordering.
This tool must be called before that
tool. The other is input hallucination.
This input must come from the output of
this tool. You don't want like a user
telling the agent be rude to me. You
don't want it to actually be rude. And
then the last one was an overall
workflow adherence. So one of the things
I noticed actually I was trying with
different I was trying out different
models and I noticed that some of the
models was interesting. I had a
confirmation step at the end. It would
do an action and then I would tell it to
I told it to send a confirmation to the
user. There were models where reliably
it would not send the confirmation to
the user because it would consider
having done the action as done. I've
asked I've done what the user asked me
to do and it would totally ignored the
part of the system instructions where I
said okay after you do this you have to
send a confirmation message. And so that
was one thing that steering guided the
model to say, you know, before returning
a model response back to the user, hey,
you're not done yet. You haven't sent
the confirmation. And so it was actually
super token efficient because I didn't
have to have this like mega system
instructions prompt defining all of
these edge cases and things like that. I
could give it general rules, bullet
points, 1 2 3 4, and then if it didn't
follow that, if it didn't adhere to
those rules, I have the steering hooks
to kind of guide it back with a little
bit of a a message back to it. And so I
was able to get that 100%
accuracy even with very small models
that we would not expect to do well with
uh being reliable. I was using GPTO OSS
12B.
>> Oh wow. So really really cheap was a lot
cheaper than to use you know a small
model plus steering than to use some of
the frontier models that would would
probably be more reliable but are also
much more costly in terms of proof
token. You mentioned token efficiency.
Did the actual I guess conversation size
or I guess task size matter but today
even though a lot of models promise the
1 million context window you would very
very hardly rarely go to the full extent
in you know or or have a session that
exploits the entire session right
because you end up having the long
context problems and all that. How did
this compare with longer context
scenarios? The only thing that I
compared was what we call SOPs, standard
operating procedures for agents. So, a
lot of what I see people trying to do to
make agents reliable is just longer
system instructions, very explicit
system instructions that define
stepbystep effectively a workflow of
steps that they wanted to take without
implementing it as a workflow. that is
not usually a million tokens, right? But
it is longer can be very verbose, right?
And you are adding to it over the over
time. I call it the prompting treadmill
where you know you start with this
pretty small prompt and then you run
into all these edge cases and you say,
"Okay, don't do that [laughter]
always." You know, use these very clear
words like always, never, must. But you
add over time to the system instructions
and then you've got this, you know,
gargantuous system instruction prompt
with all of these caveats in it and it
it does end up requiring a lot more
tokens, right? You get better accuracy,
but you don't get a 100. I actually
found that we have a tool for strands
that does generate these SOPs. It can be
useful for, you know, pretty simple use
cases or use cases where you don't
really mind it not being token
efficient. We use it a lot internally
for operations like on call
troubleshooting super easily described
as a set of steps in a system
instructions and the accuracy doesn't
need to be super high but I actually
found for this use case that I was that
I built and was evaluating with these
different techniques for steering I
found that SOPs actually achieved 99%
accuracy for the things that I was
testing for but it was three times the
input tokens.
which tend to be the expensive ones,
right? And so they don't cost as much as
as output tokens, but they can be
expensive on on big models and so more
expensive from that perspective, but you
can actually get pretty far just with a
well ststructured system instruction
set.
>> Interesting. And what about longunning
tasks? You know, long coding longunning
tasks. How does it uh fare there? I also
didn't evaluate that in particular, but
thinking about it, the like context
window management is what happens when
you get into longunning tasks, right?
And what's interesting about the
steering approach is that if you get the
full ledger, the full ledger doesn't
need like the full conversation history
effectively doesn't need to be shown to
the agent. In fact, can't be shown to
the agent when it's very long. You can
still analyze it, right? You can still
write a Python function that looks at a
huge conversation history going back
forever to determine if your rules are
still applying, if it's still adhering
to a workflow. And so that makes it a
little bit different from, you know,
let's say an LLM as judge where the
context window is going to be limited as
well or even workflows. I think what we
find with with agent workflows is that
you lose a lot of context in between the
steps, right? you have one each node in
the workflow, you lose a little bit of
context going from node to node. And so
what's interesting is you probably are
not going to build up that much that
much context, but you also are probably
missing context from from previous
decisions in the in the workflow.
>> Yeah, fair enough. How does one get
started writing one of these Python
functions to you know as steering hooks?
Like what are the gotchas? What are the
constraints?
>> Uh well, we have some pretty good
resources. I published the example the
complete example that I evaluated and
was able to get 100% accuracy on and so
that's a good place to start and then
you can also go to strandagents.com we
have a full user guide on using steering
hooks
>> switching to tools I guess you know
tools are the you know really really
integral fundamental parts of an agent
harness I think every agent understand
today integrates with tools so where
does trans take it on from how is the
tools support and integration in strands
same and different from your typical
harnesses.
>> I think that like you said every agent
framework has a tools concept has a way
that you can write tools. Strand
supports Python so you can provide like
a pedantic style function and it will
turn it into a tool. Similarly, we are
gaing the TypeScript SDK for strand. So
we're coming to a second second
language. very exciting and that also
supports providing ZOD types for
functions to turn that into a tool. We
try to make it really easy and developer
friendly to just take a regular function
and turn it into a tool. But largely we
also see MCP becoming critical to kind
of the tool ecosystem. Right? It's super
powerful to be able to pull a MCP server
off the shelf from one of your SAS
providers or you know just a utility MCP
server and connect it to to strands. And
then what I've been seeing a lot is
companies thinking about how do I
connect my internal APIs to agents now
and MCP becomes that kind of lingua
franc MCP becomes this lingua franca for
agents where you have a MCP gateway that
turns let's say an open API schema for
one of your internal APIs into an MCP
server with tools and all of a sudden
any agent developer in your company can
start to connect APIs together in really
powerful ways. So we're seeing a lot of
investment in thinking about how to
bring internal APIs to MCP just in order
to bring them to agents. That's probably
not transpecific, right? I think every
framework supports MCP, but it's
certainly becoming an important part of
agent development in general. you know,
in terms of Strand's own kind of native
tooling mechanism, right? How far do you
see taking that versus, you know,
switching more into MCP or where do you
kind of dial that knob? You know, how
would you help developers choose one or
the other?
>> The way I like to think about it is
methods versus libraries in regular
software development. When you find a
piece of code that can be used in a lot
of different places, you turn it into a
library. And I think of MCP servers and
sort of native framework specific tools
in the same way. MCP came about because
all of these frameworks had different
ways of defining tools and there wasn't
really a way to reuse them outside
[clears throat] of any particular agent
and outside of any particular framework.
So when you start to see this tool is
really valuable. I may have built it in
the strands framework or or anything
else. This tool is really valuable. I
want to share that across a lot of
agents. Turn that into an MCP server. Or
I already have this API. I want a lot of
different agents to be able to connect
to it. Turn that into an MCP server. We
still find a lot of folks writing Python
and Typescriptbased tools in Strands
using our our native support for tools.
It's really easy. It's like the easiest
way to get started when you're building
an agent and you want to add tools. You
just start to write them as Python
functions or TypeScript functions. It's
so easy, right? And then over time you
find the things that are reusable across
agents. One of the things that we
released recently is something called AI
functions which is really interesting.
We created a new GitHub organization
called Strand Labs to be a place where
we could be a bit more experimental
right internally and among users. We
have folks that are relying on Strands
for production use cases. So we don't
make a lot of breaking changes, right?
But Strand Labs is a place for us to to
kind of think boldly about where is
agent development going. One of the
things that we released is called AI
functions where today when you write a
function as a tool provide the inputs
and the outputs and then separately you
write steering hooks to validate what
the model is doing or even regular hooks
validate the inputs and the outputs to
that tool. AI functions kind of combines
them together in a crazy way. You write
a regular Python function just like you
would in strands to create a tool, but
instead of actually writing a
deterministic function, you write a
prompt for the function itself. And at
runtime, it turns that into code and
executes it. And then you can also
provide what we call preconditions and
postcond conditions. Basically, what
must be true going into this function?
like the inputs must be like this or we
must have some system has to be in this
state and then what are the post
conditions what should the output look
like what step should have been taken so
the example that I usually give is a a
method that's going to do OCR on a
receipt image and you have an image
coming in and you need structured output
coming out you need what was the total
cost on the receipt what was the vendor
what or the itemize things. So there's
some structure to it instead of trying
to write all of that OCR code yourself.
You actually have it do it at runtime.
You have it generate code at runtime,
execute code at runtime, and then you
have these preconditions like I must
have an image and then postcond
conditions like I need the structured
output and it will continue to prompt
the model. Again going back to that
feedback loop for the model and it being
so adept at self-correcting come make
sure it comes back with that structured
output from the receipt.
>> That's interesting. So did you find that
there are certain runtime or dynamic
kind of conditions in the space of
problems that the agent is solving which
I guess prevented you from left shifting
it ahead of time generation
>> because a lot of this could be generated
by our coding assistance right we no
longer have to actually write this by
hand
>> yeah yeah
>> one of the things that's interesting
about kind of the theory behind AI
functions is when you run an agent many
many times, you're probably going to get
this kind of um if you generate code
many many times against the same prompt,
you're probably going to get this like
Gaussian cloud of code solutions for it.
And some of those are optimal and some
of them are not. And when we do coding,
it's largely oneshot to the model
excepting like, you know, running it
through tests and things like that and
getting the the coding assistant to
self-correct. But what happens when you
run that a thousand times in production?
You're going to get a thousand samples
of what code is optimal. You're going to
get real runtime feedback about how did
it uh perform against real inputs, which
is hard to do in a, you know,
pre-production environment with just
test data. you're going to get
information about the latency, how often
did the model have to self-correct
itself until it achieved the post
condition. And so the theory here is
over time, can we arrive at the ideal
deterministic code and shift that left
at that point? Bring that back into the
codebase over time once we find those
very optimal solutions to some of these
problems.
>> Interesting. In fact, the way you
phrased it, the the interesting takeaway
from for me there was you can both
capture the runtime conditions across
thousand 10,000 100,000 runs and use
that as both new inputs or new
conditions for your function, right?
Hey, you know, now I'm running on a dark
background. Now I'm running on a I don't
know a different language, whatever,
right? But if that's the case, do you
ever need to have a final deterministic
version at all? Can you just go you know
what our system is it own mini
classifier that keeps generating this
classifying function or whatnot and
we'll keep using that as long as we have
the way to capture details about what is
working what's not working you know some
way of getting feedback you know
>> well that comes back to your point about
memory right if we can build a memory
system for this AI function and and
that's what we're working on now if you
can build a memory function of here's
the code that I produced. Here was the
prompt and here is how it performed.
Then the the agent can start to choose
what are the things that are bubbling up
with some amount of you know kind of
probabilistic noise to to make sure that
it's improving over time but arriving at
maybe a few optimal solutions or trying
different things over time but mostly
choosing what is the optimal solution.
So no, I don't think you ever
necessarily need to shift left,
especially as the models get better,
right? Think about all the code we wrote
with Sonnet 4 [laughter]
checked into our code bases and now we
have Opus 4.7
now. And so think about how potentially
how much better that code could be if it
was regenerated with latest models.
>> You mentioned the AI deciding what's
better, what's worse. So is AI in this
case identifying and assigning the
rewards or the rewards somewhere else?
>> That's an interesting question. And I
think we haven't really thought through
the rewards functions yet and and
potentially the rewards functions are
maybe use case specific right today the
reward function is the post condition
which is very binary right of this code
works or it doesn't work but I think we
haven't gone into defining the reward
function around the gradient of
performance or the gradient of how many
turns did it take with the model to get
it to actually produce the great result
>> or even the quality of the runtime
environment at that point in time.
>> That's right. Uh no nice looking at some
of the practical aspects u you know with
tools and the various harnesses and
strands obviously what are some of the
deployment patterns you know you've
identified you recommend you would you
would you learn from you would teach us
>> well I think the thing that we've
learned over time
using strands is start as simple as
possible the vast majority of agents
that I see
can follow the model driven approach
maybe add in hooks and and steering for
you know runtime checking but generally
speaking can be a single agent you know
I think engineers want to build and it's
easier than ever to build and so I see a
lot of engineers building these very
complex orchestration systems that for
the vast majority of use cases are are
just not necessary you're building more
than you need and so what I counel
customers on is build the simplest thing
first and evaluate and see how it does.
And often you'll be surprised. You'll be
surprised at the power of these models
that we have at our fingertips today.
The one other pattern that I do like a
lot, I don't like workflows as I think
we've talked about are graphs, but sub
agents for context management I think is
still something that is a very common
and useful pattern because even with
million token context windows, you might
not want to fill it up all the time.
With context windows that are much
lower, especially sub aents as tools are
very powerful. So effectively letting
your your main agent choose when and
which sub aents to invoke as tools. And
that's really the pattern is sub aents
as tools. And that allows you to
effectively encapsulate any contact and
thinking and tool calls that the sub
agent is doing while it's executing on a
very particular task. One that I have
used recently was I built an agent that
needed to go pull a bunch of websites
and get very specific information from
each website. Extract like an event for
example from a from a bunch of different
websites. That's a ton of context to
carry around for your entire agent. And
so the main agent was able to invoke a
sub agent whose sole job was to extract
an event, pull one website, extract
event, return event. And so instead of
carrying around, you know, the full HTML
content from all of these pages, it was
able to return to the Ma agent just that
event and throw away the rest. That's
very much a pattern that I that I love
and use. And you know it's almost like
uh we are going to the roots of software
engineering. You're writing functions
and not one big function
>> and you can get very very sophisticated
with it of like having an input schema
and an output schema for your sub agents
literally just like functions right we
are learning encapsulation [laughter]
all over again.
No, no, it's interesting how we I mean
in a way look if it's improving the
awareness and appreciation for soften
engineering I think that's amazing right
sub agents one thing what are multi-
aent multi- aent capabilities you know I
guess without generalizing sub agents as
multi- aents where would you draw the
parallel where would you draw the line
how would you kind of you know look at
what Strand offers today
>> yeah so strands offers multi- aent
patterns and and we offer a really great
guide on our website at strandagents.com
that that walks you through kind of
generally with this model driven
approach when should you think about
using some of these patterns versus
again the vast majority of use cases
that just need a simple simple agent
multi- aent I find most use cases don't
need what I will say is I find that they
are often necessary for organizational
reasons rather than technical reasons
what I mean by that is let's think about
microservices. Why did we move to
microservices? Because different teams
can own different logic and they can
move independently of of other teams and
we can have APIs as the contract between
us. What I'm seeing in companies that do
have these multi-agent use cases is
often it's kind of like microservices.
We've got micro micro agents where one
team is owning an agent and another team
is trying to integrate with that agent.
that agent becomes an API that is called
and you start to get into these, you
know, multi- aent use cases as opposed
to a simple tool that's calling a simple
API. These agents are going off and
doing work and they're long running and
so the interaction pattern looks a
little bit different from from typical
tools. I see that a lot and and that
again, you know, coming back to software
engineering basics, it it feels very
much like that, you know, that the
separation of of concerns for more
organizational reasons, which is also
valid, right? But a little bit less than
this would also probably be just as
accurate and powerful if it was
allin-one system.
>> Yeah. And what are some of the
communication p patterns that differ
from sub agents versus multi- aent? You
know, you know, how would you kind of
characterize those? What I tend to see
is folks trying to think about how much
of the previous context from the main
agent needs to go into the sub agent or
the other agent. Exactly. Sometimes for
very well scoped tasks very little.
Right. In my example of pull down a
website extract event all that sub agent
or even if that was another agent owned
by a different team all it needs is a
URL to go and pull. It doesn't need any
of the previous context. But if you
think about, you know, maybe a very
complex process like
refund processing is a big one. Um,
everybody wants to automate refund
processing, but that touches so many
different systems and some of those
teams have built different agents and so
you start to build up a lot of context
for what what those different agents
need. It needs to know what is the item,
what is the risk profile for this
customer, what interactions have you had
with the customer already about
returning this item and what did they
say. So I think it depends on just kind
of what the use case is and what the sub
aents maybe need and that's going to be
dependent on on the use case of what
those do, right? What is the information
they need to be as accurate as possible?
I mean if you remove the LM for a second
from all this then you're describing or
or we're talking about giant giant
orchestration workflow you know various
kinds of saga patterns all over the
place right so it's almost like you know
90% of this plumbing that has to go no
matter what you know what is building it
or who's building it
>> you can imagine you know in those those
orchestration systems we've had shared
documents right that describe what's
happened so far what is the information
so you can think about that a shared
document for all of these these sub
agents but then again you have to worry
about the context window right yeah
>> which reminds me so context window is
one thing what a history I mean history
across agents is it more for
resumability model is it a transfer
model you know when I say model I don't
mean the LM just a pattern you know like
how is history I guess managed in this
scenario or in this setup
>> I think one of the changes that I've
seen with harnesses in particular is a
different way of thinking about history.
Often with a harness, you're going to
call the same agent over and over again
until done, right? We have the wealth
Ralph Wigum loop effect, right? But that
means that agent needs to save important
information somewhere. Even if it's
thinks it's done, it needs to save what
is the state of things that you have
left it in. In coding, this is, you
know, what is the state of tasks, coding
tasks that you've done. But in other
agents, it's going to be something else.
Basically, like save my state to disk.
And often it's just disk, which is so
like easy and nice. But then when the
agent wakes up again because it's not
actually done, it can resume from that
natural language description that it
saved for itself and its past its past
life. Right? So it's almost like I think
of it like you know sometimes at the end
of the day I'll download my brain into
you know obsidian or something like that
so that the next day I one so I don't
have to think about it at night and two
so that the next day I wake up and I say
oh what was I thinking about yesterday
what did I want to get done in the
morning there it is. It's kind of just
like that with agents and they're very
good at prompted to kind of save the
state of their work and then resume from
that. I think that's the biggest thing
that I've seen, biggest pattern I've
seen emerge just in the last like four
months as agents agent harnesses started
to get popular is that kind of save your
work pattern which is completely outside
of conversation history right it's about
the agent itself almost summarizing what
are the important things to resume from
the context window that I have
>> what if History itself was a tool. Let's
say if history was nothing special and
if it just happened to be a tool call
that the agent knows how to effectively
call. Do you see anything happening in
that sense or is that even useful? Is
that valuable? Is that just
>> I've seen that used for a while. I mean
in a lot of agent memory systems. You
have kind of three different levels of
agent memory. You have that quote
unquote short-term memory which is not
necessarily short-term, right? It can go
for a long time, but it's that
conversation history, that raw
conversation history that the agent has
the tail end of it basically, but you
can search back in time so that somebody
can say, "What were we talking about
yesterday?" Right? And it can go back
and and look at that raw conversation
history. and then kind of the what some
people kind of call medium-term or
long-term where it's you just have a
kind of a rolling summary of the
conversation history, but you're going
to lose a lot of important details in
that. And so then you get to this like
semantic memory where you pull out these
again these nuggets, right? this person
likes Java over Typescript or this
person has a very somebody told me was
looking at what their agent had saved in
its memory and said this person uses a
lot of Britishisms [laughter]
uses a lot of British slang so and and
for whatever reason the model thought
that was very important for its future
interactions right so letting the model
decide what's important
>> okay fair enough I think history and
memory we keep going well it's only been
18 months but we do keep going kind of
back and forth on that dial right so
you'll just see kind of where they land
I want to you know touch base on some of
the production aspects of your
deployments I mean AWS strands is you
know very heavily used in AWS from what
I'm hearing I'd love to learn more about
the lessons from scale on which products
how does the product specific thing come
in
>> well we worked really hard to make sure
that strands was production ready what I
mean by that is that you don't have to
add in all of the things you need to put
it in production. It supports open
telemetry out of the box so that you get
observability over traces and metrics
things like that. We added in out of the
box session persistence so that you can
save it to S3 or a file or whatever it
may be because that's very important
once you get into production to actually
persist these things. And we did that
first for ourselves, right? We were
building production systems with this.
That let us build and get agents to
production really quickly. Within three
to six weeks is what we were seeing for
time to deploy these these new agents to
production. And we've seen that over and
over again inside of Amazon as as well
as outside. We just recently added a
managed kind of a managed strands
service called agent core harness that
runs strands under the hood, but it also
combines in all of the other things that
you need like a memory system, an
identity system. What is the identity of
the agent? How does it get credentials?
all of the observability information
going into Cloudatch, connectivity to
your MCP gateway, you know, all of these
things that you do still have to set up
when you are creating an agent. You have
to deploy it somewhere to some runtime.
Agent core harness takes care of
deploying it to a new VM. Connectivity
to the models, all of these things that
are are still steps that you need to
take to get it into production. So,
agent core harness takes out a lot of
that work and just lets you provide what
is the model, what is the prompt, what
are the tools so that you can focus on,
you know, what is it that you want the
agent to do instead of kind of all of
this other stuff that you we've seen
customers build over and over and over
again to get into production.
>> Oh, nice. How can customers today you
know use open telemetry for example or
traces for example to I guess walk
through AC agent you know a core harness
right to understand I guess which path
the agent took at various parts of the I
guess run
>> so locally you can just see them get you
know dumped out of the uh open telemetry
exporter you know it's interesting I was
I was looking for a really good desktop
application for looking at open
telemetry traces I feel like there's not
a great one. So, you know, if somebody
wants to build that, I would I
[laughter] would love to use it, you
know, in production and in in your
testing environments, you can export it
to, you know, your favorite hotel
compliant provider, be that Cloudatch or
any other tracing provider, and use
their visualization to kind of walk
through what it is that the agent does
because it it's going to show you all of
the things that you just don't see when
you get the final output out of the
agent and you're wondering what just
happened? How did it arrive at this
conclusion? You know, so you can see the
tool calls that it made, the tool
inputs, the outputs, the thinking that
it did as it was, you know, choosing the
tool like, ah, I need to do this first,
now I need to do this. Seeing that is
super useful in working back from what
the result was to what actually happened
there. And then, you know, you can also
use those for offline evaluation. Those
are super valuable for once you've run
this agent in production, you know, a
thousand times, being able to look
across and say, how many of these
trajectories do I think are good and how
do I, you know, maybe tune the system
prompt or the the steering hooks or
something to make these trajectories a
little bit better? And then, you know,
looking at again using that same offline
evaluation with whatever system prompt
tweaks or thing that you're doing. And
then often we see customers investing in
AB testing because it's so hard to test
agents. It really is. And sometimes
there's just no
replacement for testing it with real
customers, right, when with these
agents. And so before, you know, even at
Amazon, in AWS, we'd never really
invested in AB testing because we would
always do just testing [laughter] like
we would just have, you know,
deterministic tests. You give this this
input to the API, you get this output
back, it works, right? But with agents,
it's obviously not true. You're not
going to get the same answer twice. And
so we've started investing in AB testing
for agents quite a bit internally for
our own agents because it can be very
difficult to
predict what are people going to ask
this thing or what inputs are are they
going to give and it's very challenging
to confidently roll out changes to your
tools to your tool descriptions to your
system prompt to the model even you know
just going 100%. And so, yeah, we've
been doing a lot more AB testing where
we roll out to, you know, 10% of users
for a couple of weeks and and see how it
goes.
>> It's like changing every part of your
car while driving it, right? I mean,
[laughter]
>> in terms of adoption and and best
practices, I think you mentioned, you
know, start off small, start off simple,
right? What are some of the common
anti-atterns and mistakes you see
developers kind of make when they, you
know, start off with agents beyond, you
know,
>> they build too much
>> [laughter]
>> you know, playing with agents is so fun.
And so I can't blame people for wanting
to just build a bunch of stuff around
agents. And I think also people build
agents when they probably could have
built an MCP server, for example. That
is that's one thing that we're seeing a
lot internally is uh we went through a
year like two years ago where it was
like okay everybody's going to build an
agent and then we ended up with a
million agents right and there's a lot
of overlap between them of course and
it's very hard to understand when to use
what agent and so I think now we're on a
path of well maybe everybody should just
provide context to a few central agents
everybody's got an agent agent harness
in their pocket now with coding
assistance. Everybody's got um access to
to easily build an agent harness with
strands. But often I think the question
to ask yourself is should you be
building an agent for this or should you
provide context to a centralized agent?
That's really the process that we're
going through now where we're trying to
figure out what is that data that we
want to make available to agents. So uh
recently at at AWS we put the AWS MCP
server in preview. What that does is
provides
uh tools for agents to call AWS APIs and
retrieve skills about how to do things
with multiple AWS APIs. And the the
learning there was instead of trying to
do this kind of provide an agent for
example and and try to expose it over
A2A and all of this probably our users
just want an MCP server and have their
agent do it themselves. That's a lot
simpler. That's a current pattern for me
is is pushing teams to actually not
build an agent sometimes and and instead
to think about what are other ways to
make your data and your context
available to agents
>> and as they do this what would be like a
minimum set of things that they monitor
and kind of observe early on at least to
know that your agent isn't kind of going
off the rails soon than later.
Evaluation is super important for both
creating agents and even MCP servers
because if you think about the tools
that are available through your MCP
server, that's going to impact people's
agents. If your tool descriptions aren't
good, the agents using that MCP server
are not going to be very powerful. So
evaluation is super important and
figuring out what is it that you want to
evaluate for. I always tell people if
you want to build an agent, start with a
use case where you can deterministically
evaluate trajectories. So things like
were the right tools called for a
particular input? Were they called in
the right order? Um did they have the
right inputs? The harder things to
evaluate are things like chat bots are
honestly really difficult to evaluate
because you've got these multi-turn
conversations and you end up trying to
do these LLM judges around like how good
is this conversation? I don't know. It's
kind of up to the user how they felt
about it, right? But a lot of these
automation use cases are actually really
great lowhanging fruit because they can
be evaluated against some kind of
existing process.
>> As we wrap up, what's next for strands?
What's what's what's in your kind of
horizon?
>> We are going farther into supporting
folks who are building agents on top of
an agent harness. I think that is really
with the power of models today. There's
so much power around that that's been
enabled for agent harnesses. And so I
think a lot more around how do you keep
agents running for a long time? What are
the things that you need out of your
agent harness to do that? And what are
the new patterns for agents? Things like
event driven agents, very very
longunning agents that are interruptible
are all in my mind right now. Where can
our listeners learn more about strands
and get started?
>> strandsagents.com.
>> Are you presenting any other
communities? Are you talking elsewhere?
Do you have any conference coming up
that they can listen to you?
>> Oh, [laughter]
okay. All good. We will definitely be
adding all the resources that you
mentioned here in the show notes and in
the page itself. Any last words of
wisdom for our listeners?
>> Have fun with agents. Start with model
tools prompt.
>> Awesome. Thank you. Thank you. Thank you
very much, Clay, for joining us on
Software Engineering Radio.
>> Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
Ile E Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamseradio.net. [music]
This and all other episodes of SE radio
is licensed under Creative Common
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.